<!--
BEGIN_COPYRIGHT

Copyright (C) 2013-2014 CRS4.

This file is part of vispa.

vispa is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify it under the
terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the Free Software
Foundation, either version 3 of the License, or (at your option) any later
version.

vispa is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT ANY
WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR
A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along with
vispa.  If not, see <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/>.

END_COPYRIGHT
-->

<tool id="annotate" name="Annotate ISs" version="0.9.0">

<description></description>

<command interpreter="python">
  annotate.py $input_file $annot_file -o $output_file $skip_first $multi
</command>

<inputs>
  <param name="input_file" type="data" format="tabular"
	 label="ISs, one tab-separated (chr, pos) pair per line" />
  <param name="skip_first" type="boolean" checked="False"
	 truevalue="--skip-first" falsevalue="" label="Skip first line" />
  <param name="multi" type="boolean" checked="False"
	 truevalue="--multi" falsevalue="" label="Extended output" />
  <param name="annot_file" type="data" format="bed"
	 label="Annotation file in BED format" />
</inputs>

<outputs>
  <data name="output_file" format="tabular" label="Annotated ISs"/>
</outputs>

  <help>
**What it does**

This tool takes two input files:

1. A tabular file with one integration site (IS) per line. Each
   integration site is represented by a tab-separated (chromosome,
   position) pair. Columns beyond the second one, if present, are
   ignored.

2. An annotation file in BED format. In addition to the three required
   BED fields (chromosome tag, start, end), this tool also requires the
   name and strand fields to be present. Note that since the BED format
   has no header and does not allow "holes" in between columns, a fifth
   column for the score field must be present (it will be ignored) before
   the strand column.

**Make sure that chromosome tags are consistent between the
two input files.**

For each input IS, the tool finds the closest feature among
those listed in the provided annotation file and
outputs annotation information in the following format::

  CHROM POS NAME START END STRAND TSS_D REL_POS INTEGRATION

Where whitespace characters represent tabs and:

CHROM, POS are taken from the corresponding input query

NAME and STRAND are the feature's name and strand as they appear in
the annotation file

START, END are the feature's starting and ending position. Note that,
in contrast with the convention used in bed files, END is not
augmented by one

TSS_D is the distance from the transcription start site (START if the
strand is positive or END if it's negative)

REL_POS is the relative position of the integration site with respect
to the feature. Possible values are::

  -1 if POS &lt; START on the positive strand or POS &gt; END on the negative
  0 if POS is contained within the feature
  1 if POS &lt; START on the negative strand or POS &gt; END on the positive

INTEGRATION is the integration percentage, expressed as ``100 * TSS_D / (END - START)``

**Extended output**

Since annotated genomic regions are often overlapping, an IS can be
contained within (or equally close to) multiple features: if the
extended output flag is activated, for each IS the program outputs
multiple lines corresponding to such features; otherwise, it picks one
at random.
  </help>
</tool>
